Good, yeah.
Welcome.
Thank you for coming to the session.
Help via enjoyed the morning...the keynote
...of dour and I'm here with ism anand...and we are program managers and we
are passionate about open-source how many of you are using
open-source libraries and tools in your projects.
Fantastic.
So, we work with engineering teams at microsoft on integrating open-source into
windows.
contributing to open-source projects that many of us are using to build apps projects like open
sl and seeming.
And, we're here to share with you some examples and demos how
you can use some new ways that you can use open-source when you're building apps for windows.
We're going to start with an overview of microsoft and open-source what's going on with the microsoft
culture.
What is microsoft think about open-source today we're going to dive into the demos and
...spend most of the time in the demos?
And,...wrap up with what's happening in visual studio and how visual
studio is doing more and more to support developing using open-source?
The start with a question.
...microsoft embrace
open-source would love to get your feedback on this is something that there's been an are passionate
about how many feel like microsoft is doing a great job of embracing open-source.
So, maybe two so...three-out-of-four stars is that.
Right that's great I mean we want to get to for
...working on it so here's how I would answer that question.
That it's changed over time and I want to roll the clock back to start in two thousand
one and let's review how microsoft has engage with the open-source community.
So, what was happening in...one well there are some major
open-source projects that we're getting a lot of publicity
...linux?
Netscape.
And, it was a time from microsoft to decide how did...want to engage with open-source.
This was a rough start from microsoft there was a real opportunity here.
And, it wasn't simple.
Gps licensing was a curve ball it wasn't just a
curable from microsoft was for many companies but I like baseball
I'm going to use a baseball analogy here it's baseball season
microsoft having a hard time at the plate let's move on...
So,...twenty-four microsoft made its first contribution to source forge with the
wicks installer toolkit and from then on we see increasing involvement with the
...community contributions to linux and...
And, other projects consumption more teams internally are starting to use open-source.
Publishing clearly with
the net foundation when js you're seeing more and more microsoft activity with
publishing projects into the open-source community and working with the community.
And, redistributing...a great example of this
were asher looked at an opportunity to embrace open-source and, you know,
what they did they did embrace open-source and the result is a much better service
for you in a much better business for the company so now microsoft getting hits?
So, what's different about twenty fifteen.
We've had...we've had some stars you've seen these stars.
One twenty fifteen the company is adopting
open-source as a company.
...now coulda walk around campus and talk about open-source.
We also embrace the philosophy of transparency.
Collaborating with the larger community.
We also embrace those social model so you have your commanders and
contributors and users and that model works fantastic for open-source project
also works internally so at some teams are starting
to apply this and how they're setting up internally so if you're in some
...microsoft's a big company right if you see a project that you're interested in you
can get involved even though it's not in your core subject area we use the open-source social models support that?
And, best practices we've had some
stars companies learn from what the stars of done.
And, we've created best practices so that other groups who haven't been
stars now have a roadmap for how to get there.
So, this is all in this is where microsoft is that today.
And, it's fantastic for us who love open-source.
So, let's talk about house microsoft been involved lately.
Well, it's across-the-board game middleware
media services databases tools you name it
microsoft been involved there's a ton of open-source projects that you
can use today I'll just touch on a few here open cv.
So, that's computer vision...a open-source library can use for facial recognition of the features
like that and microsoft engineers have been working with open singly so that you can use open cv
in your apps and publish them to the store same thing with coca studio
access very popular gaming middleware and multiple groups in microsoft working with
...to dx so that you can have a great experience building coca studio
x for windows and publishing those games in-store and then dashed
js is a javascript library.
That you can use to add dash adaptive streaming protocol which
is fairly new so teams...microsoft been contributing to the dashed...project so
you can easily ad that dash player to a web page or...app.
So, those are some great examples.
The company adoption of open-source is also showing up in other ways.
So, now you can become a microsoft mvp.
Solely based on open-source contributions.
So, that's fantastic another one is let's look at what the eighteen is doing.
So, they have a status site is open to everyone and you can see
...backlog
and you can go vote and what you want the ie team to work on next?
So, when I saw this is just fantastic love the transparency?
And, not only that but you can see wthree-c status of web pep platform status.
And, people in the community are using this as a
way to track what's happening across browsers you can see some...logos there so for each feature you can see
what the statuses with the other browsers and the eighteen put the source for
this site upon get hub so anyone in the community if they see something they want to
be done better or something's not
quite accurate about some certain browser they can go and make this fixes and they're doing that so it's a great
example of how microsoft as embracing open-source.
So, back to the question.
Does microsoft embrace opensource yes absolutely?
And, we're committed to getting better we know we have work to do.
And, part of part of our goal with build is to get more
of your feedback we want to learn about what's working well for you
and what isn't and what can we do to help so...are going to be around and we're going to want to have
this conversations with you because your feedback will make a big impact
on what we work on next we have engineers and teams that are focused on...
All right so now this one's going to.
Dive into the next section take it away
...all right thank you thank you use a for that overview...thank you all for coming out
to san francisco and to build it's an absolute pleasure to
...representing before you guys thank you very much.
So, now we're going to.
Talk about open-source in windows...
Upping
redmond you're spending a lot of time thinking how us developers can
be more and do more using windows and we think that by leveraging open-source
technology we can make windows a more powerful platform for your applications?
Around the company we're saying that we're shipping a new mindset not just new features and
you api and this mindset involves embracing open-source at each level in are
stuck.
We're using open-source and some of our flagship applications says escape
...dina the photos app many of the msn apps that you get
out of box then we're...in our sdk all join the internet of
...software a framework is a great example of that going to get into that with that and then we
are shipping open-source in our core mission critical os components that
run across all the devices in the windows...family ranging from small
io devices to the tablet
do the xbox and all the way to haul...
So, let's look at some of the investments that we've made or the last few months.
You really excited about working closely with...like.
So, we love your code we know that you love to work with...I
did thousands of apps in our store today that use this library for data access we
want to make it run better on windows
they ever did before and for that we're working very closely with the
sql like architect richard hip thanks richard for all your help and score development team and
...core engineers doctor them on how.
We can...sequel light and what changes we can make the operating system so that when the
to come together you get better performance as a user and developer?
Sql it is also a great way to do local data access in your universal windows
applications it words great on all the devices in the family especially resource constraint
devices such as mobile phones and the devices that comprise the internet of things.
For those a few who are coming from the enterprise from the
dot net world you might be you might have use entity framework
...so entity framework seven is now going to
works with universal windows application and
you'll be able to use it with the local database for local storage which is going to be sequel.
So, let's get into our force demo which is.
Lightweight to do list averages tightly coupled with
...example...cplus-plus application.
Your own...
You see...learns find attribution.
All right.
So,...have a simple to do list...has basic categories for different type of tasks
...personal family and,
they'll start...tasks as a program manager I have to reply
do a lot of emails that I haven't in a while since I'm here so
I'll reply...a lot of emails.
Go ahead add another task right.
Actually finish all
...writing it finish this specks.
And, then I'm going to...up another demo.
Stepson work tasks here.
Now in preparation of this talk I haven't really clean-up my apartment in
a while so I'm going to go out a personal task so...
...added tasks to each of my categories and this is basically just storing it in a local
...database according to these categories I can after I'm done with my
work day I can go get rid of all of these here so they're gone.
And, I can view the rest in the all category it's fairly simple
...stab and now we're going to we can start stepping
through the code and see how it works with sequel...
The start this off with...
The launch...the butter.
So, on launching here I'm just calling the...you sizes so you can actually.
See what's going on the side.
Another exciting...so on launching I'm just calling
sequel light open which if there's a sequel light
database file already sitting on your in your apps local data for it would just open that
all-in-one
...create a new one since we're opening this for the first-time it's going to I
have this creative function let's see what's going on in there so in this
creative function once you create a sequel lightbulb file it doesn't
have cable so here I'm just defining that table and...
...a create statement heregiving it the columns that I
...my table then I perform the sequel like prepare
on it which turns the...statement into byte code I do sequel
...step which make sure that it's the right sequel statements valid and then it
call...light finalize and it goes and creates my table.
And, then I basically just small this...refresh,
refresh list function which is reads data from the table
that can display that right now it's an empty table so you don't see anything.
So, now let's go...ask and see what happens.
On work it's refreshing the list but now it's telling sequel light that it
wantsdatajust for the work category which is represented by
an integer here which we passed through...sql statement.
So, I did...demo I
...the add button it took me here where I'm just.
Calling and...item function let's see what's in there
I'm in this function I'm just I just have an insert into the
...database for this particular category which is work.
And, then I refresh the list
again to get fresh data from the database and I've just store I
just stored writer demo in there so you can see that.
it's a fairly it's fairly easy to use equal light...universal windows applications from a cplus-plus
up if you're if you will be hacking around with the...later on be getting a lot of
requests for that you can download the vsix for universal windows application from the
sequel...website.
Get-go it.
Cool so let's...which that presentation...
So, that was a simple
lightweight do list demo for the...sequel...
And, now let's talk about how we're using sequel
light to do local data access in the operating system we are storing all of windows
...state data in a sql light database
so up to windows eight we had multiple data stores across
are all the devices that we supported in multiple database technologies on the
same device and...engineers moving forward when...creating a converged operating system wanted a
single data store that perform well and was easier to up to
...to maintain so they look at all the...were already using but they also
look at open-source auctions options outside of microsoft and the value and...also
...sequel eight in the performance testing we found that
sql it actually perform great for the read heavy scenarios that are
...guys...looking for so we adopted that and, we shipping that on all the devices.
And, then we took...step back and we like we
realized we did a scan of the windows code base and we realize that there are other things that, you know,
they want you...as well...like all right let's why not just collect
device this effort and we come up with some center processes and
policiesto manage sequel light in the operating system so it's easier for teams
that are consuming it of want to consumer in the operating system to up...on
board so right now if you want to use the open-source software in analyst
...you have to go to legal and you have to do a bunch of stuff like ip scanning so we just centralized
...so all they have to do is go and...dependency...
And, we're also working closely with the
...like...developers to see how this can work a bit of how the library can work better under.
So, we've delve into deep into favorite of
detail now let's start talking about abstraction and comes to abstraction a lot of you might
like rms ...entity framework seven is are preferred or I am for the
universe windows application platform right now so,
let's take a look into this some people like to talk to
the databases directly right...for that which is fine if you're using
...can help you abstract away a lot of the details
...can focus on the business logic in the user experience so specially for
lb apps I when I'm writing my demos I prefer to use that.
So, here I have a simple.
...some of the right one.
So, in have universal windows application
up its for shipping company it's for the of
...employees at a retail store and what they can do using this is they
And, fetch...orders from their companies cloud.
Then they can assign those orders for themselves if they think they can fulfill it I think we
can fulfill this...orange...and I'm going one right now so, yeah,
go for app so let's do this so of
assigned to myself it has updated that...this assigned to the
...in the cloud and now I'm going to go around the warehouse
...packaging this order but I'm going to go offline because I
...running around...looks and trainees...have spotting connection of
...minded can internet connection off but all this the
...assigned to myself a store locally now so I'm going to
...open this order I'm going around.
...disable the break points here.
So, I...both of these...them off...them and I...this order
is shipped ask for...but now tells me that cannot be march
shipped in the cloud because I'm not connected to the internet and that I
showed you pressing button when I'm back online so now I don't have
any orders anymore but I need to still let the cloud
...that I've taken care of this I'm going to connect back to the internet.
I'm going to go...this.
And, now has updated that state in the cloud...ship and its march shipped
done your I can do choose orders again now I just have one order new
...came in less work from possible.
So, let's step to the scored and I'll show you how simple it is to do this with entity framework and sequel.
I'm going to...points on.
Great points.
So, the first thing that I'm doing
inherent inside the code a few using entity framework you probably have define models.
So, I create to models...create the order model that's basically I have
to classes for them you can see what's in the order model right over here
is it has a boolean of...shipped are not of it that shipment synched with the
cloud are not with some other information and this maps exactly to the
...object that I get from the cloud law so I take...object
serialized into an object up into an instance of this I have a
list of items which I call the order lines so shirts the?
The...that stuff that's required for that particular order...mention in there so
haven't and then I...order line model whether that orders backdoor...when we were like clicking,
clicking dates...basically just checking this particular property then I have a
...simple context where...entity framework that these are the two entities the order and
the order lines that I needed data store for.
And, then here is the cool part of this where I ham?
Basically I'm.
Creating a local database.
In my local order form application data and I'm
...the entity framework here to use...light...passing it the bat
...where I want and this is the only...encode where you would see a reference to
...lights abstracted abstracts everything away so,
let's see what happens when you actually goal and.
So, when you go and fill in order and you and you click?
Click on one of the one of the items.
It changes that state immediately to the database.
And, then it checks
...all the items have been back so that it can lead the order
ship if they're all packed and I click the ship
button it would ask me to confirm the shipment at the same time and I would confirm
it would save that state the database then it would try to contact the cloud.
Yeah, so,...true.
If it goes through the...call.
So, yeah, so, here's just marking the order.
Think that's true if it if it actually
...back from the cloud and successfully able to save that.
So, let me show you the...
Yeah, so.
So, here's the thing logic where tries to contact unicorns store
serviceif the order that I'm trying to think is actually shipped
...can...will update that in the database or...would just show me a dialogue
...could not connect and that actually practicing later
so that's a very lightweightdevil of how you can use entity framework this would be online
...miller's also giving a more detail talk
on entity framework so you guys check it out of its on thursday?
So, there's more to entity framework seven how many of
you are involved in open-source project.
Are managing in open-source project...to start in open-source project?
Or some of you so there's some good lessons that we can take away from entity framework
entity framework has been fully open-source for a while...building entity framework seven on get
...you can goal see their source more than that...publishing all of their
...consuming open-source themselves and their publishing all of their engineering nodes
there design documents they meeting notes on get up so people can...
What's going in to the framework and lights going in and they have a
rising number of a contributors and community rounded is growing with people are going in there
file...fat...finding bugs they're making you design suggestions and
to these meeting nodes they can see where design suggestions...and the high-level take away from that team we
were talking the those folks a few weeks earlier was that...if
...transparent with your open-source project you can really build a community
...and it helps you develop a better product as...
So, let's shift gears and talk about the internet of things
this is a partnership I'm really excited about so, all join as
you mentioned before is a software framework to talk to connected devices
a microsoft shipping this as part of the sdk.
And, microsoft also six up as a is also part of the all
seen alliance which is a consortium of all the of many
appliance manufacturers and software companies are working on all join specifically like lg electra
...those guys are making
appliances they already have some the market they're making more that
...join enabled and windows it a fair amount of work on this front are all
join in the...joint image engineers they work on decor development groups
...defining the core frameworks...security
being spent a fair amount of work security testing all
join defining this design for that and they've contributed that work back to the community?
All join is a great way to make connected apps.
Up on the universal using the universal
up platform.
You can make abstract can talk to ineligible tv
...life fix bulbs or you can make your own device up using
raspy by and then make it...to your app it also come...part of the
sdk you can also use which...very sport in visual...to learn for it.
Demo time yet let's do the demo so I'm going to quickly demo.
Like the all joint concept here of how you can make.
En-us windows application that...to and all...device.
So, here I have an application.
That I will use to control my daughter which is all joined enable.
Fire up the...as well.
Samoa.
...closer...right over here.
And, now so, ...
Representing that...device by this by this app that have over here you could deployed on or
asking by...work elsewhere but essentially...two separate applications
apl connected to each other...over the all join network that both have joint
...launched them so I can do start toasting here and then say when the
...done someone would trigger the...done signal.
And, then I get a notification my notification center just like I would get a notification from
my email that...done.
Let's quickly stepped to the code for this not going to go too much into debt because we have
an...session going on in parallel you should
...that online...they will
get into the details of the architecture but basically here I have.
My devices represented by.
And, all join produces like I call they
call it the producer because it's producing the notification and then it simply registers...
...network using in all join bus and it starts off
...service
...starts...that hey I'm available I can talk to other apps and
the cool thing to note here is that you don't have to install any additional library to do this
work you can just start using this name space windows dot devices dot all...and your...
On my side.
Samoa.
So, all...basically starting
a toaster watcher which would look for this particular device.
On the network...launch my app the...are added then I launch my all
join toaster device and it says something
that says hey I'm available to connectwhich fires off this still...added?
Added event and then it can start receiving signals here.
Cool...it's all running off the all join infrastructure
...wi-fi network that both are...
So, yeah, that's so...one that's a cool demo.
But, you know,
I think there's another cool way we can show all join working and I think you're talking
...it's you're and you're out...your torch yes let's show them the
...the shown the torch yet not quite done yet we're working on it so I want
...torch that I can get a around at my house...
So, that I can sink the lights on the...my music that I'm playing
...all join speak that's right so we got this torch app is...the
...of...going on is this is running on my laptop and...talking to this router and the
...is also talking to this router so it's an order network right here on stage so that's just the our
cord yet and basically just a...in...assembles
...make one so this is a windows app and we got a few things we can.
...working...networking...
Okay, maybe we'll have to come back to that demo...it is an alpha.
...down launch...yeah,...try one more time.
Or make sure I could see it.
There's no problem you're not so we went connected to
...wiser so, ...or homeland...
Answer yes I want to.
So, this is a tool that basically when it is
...other altering devices available just...the...line.
All right hopefully that works and see if we can see the device whoops.
Thanks networking ok.
Let me do the other demo and if we...I was I come back to
...anyway...it's cool it does work but we are the we are the bleeding at you.
All right so now I'm going...the next demo.
And, start with the scenario so let's say you want to build a media...
And, you want to supporter broad-range of codecs and.
The first-place...you look at the windows media
...and the platform support for media and they've done a ton of
great work there there's another session all the stuff they've been doing and you get a
lot of great features you get your audio and video sinking and
the hardware decoder so especially...mobile it's not going to during the battery nearly as fast as software
...coders so you're looking at that and there's a lot of great popular codecs that are supported
there but in your app you want you want broader support for different codecs.
So, in open-source world there's...mpeg and fm
...is a great open-source library and the team and working...look at
...and unpack and, said well how can we make it easier to use...of
...your apps and at the same time how can you leverage in that same
...the windows media pipelines what they came up with is fm pick interop...this is up
on get have now and you can come join us make it better
where it's actively being worked on and me show you how it works.
Simple app going to pick a local file.
...and creative.
Creative commons content this big
but money because probably seen as if you're working with media.
Ok, so, there's just playing the app.
So, here's our open local file all this code is doing is opening a file
picker identifying the...want to play.
It creates a file stream to that the passes that file stream into fm
...interop library what you get back from
fm pick interop is a media stream source that's a
generic class that you can use to represent media for...media pipeline.
You can assign that media stream source to a media element in
...so it's just a few lines of code...current media player.
Let me show you a little more let's step in the...this time.
...that same clip you can just see the code.
All right so here now we're in that were inside fm...interop and the idea is that when
you using fm pick interop you don't need to touch this...just going to do the right thing for years
want to show you what it's doing so here...unpacked that file we gave its
...container and its...audio stream.
And, it's just going to look at what's the codec it sees that
...knows that are media platform has support for ac so it's not going to decompress it.
...the video stream.
It...explore.
And, it says I'm going to leave this compressed and what the windows media pipeline handle this content?
It all comes back as a media stream sourcing gets...to that media element.
Now broad codec support.
And, open a dot org file.
This you cannot just click and file explore and play in windows.
Same code going to look at the codec.
It's going to see that it's...
...say no I I'm going to have to decompress that
...software the software...so does that.
Same thing with the video.
Codec is your.
And, it's going to use it's going to create uncompressed with the software...coders.
But, for the user of this libraries same code
your applying the resulting media stream source to that media element.
So, very cool I think this is a great example of microsoft
engineers being creative about how you can use the best in the windows platform and
leverage open-source in your projects in a simple way we're still working on this
we'd love to have people that are interested in this project to get involved...up and get up now.
All right so that's it for demos.
And, bummed about the...have to set up the...awareness shown working because it works with
...and if you want to help us make the lapped better make a cool torch.
...a parties going...can flash green when you're when you're phone's ringing you can't hear your
phone and some great ideas right let's look back to the...
Your favorite id supporting more of the project types that you love.
So, visual studios always been my favorite id...do you guys feel the same way about visual studio
...a fantastic id...right.
And, but, sometimes...had projects in the past perhaps...using a language
a particular project...well I have to use this other thing over here would be great if you could just stay
in visual studio the time that's what they're working on so let's give you some examples.
Get hub.
You're going to be able to work in visual
studio and never leave the id e in manager general projects.
Awesome right.
So, there a couple open-source projects that are behind this and they're libm get...libm get to
...these...get help check them out and the great story here is that
it's microsoft engineers working with get
...engineers and the community alta pull this together
integrate way to definitely check this out.
Cordova if
...interested or doing cordova app development visual studios
now bundling more and more of the dependencies that you need with cordova you
can see some big ones in their node is in the installer now.
An android sdk.
Is pretty cool?
So, cordova if you're not familiar is
...using web languages to build apps which html javascript and
...gets package into...that you can just you can a...store.
Python handsome and as an article on this about how
this particular tools is fantastic if you're working with python.
It's on get...microsoft tvs and this is actively continually being work
tumbles already great.
So, you get...teller sense you get syntax
...can step through it all within visual studio to definitely check that out.
And, node js in visual studio we saw this
I got so excited because I use node...on my on my own love node but,
the thought of staying in visual studio and setting break points and even with remote
servers that you're interacting with a lot on the screen there...
just let you kind of digest that if you're bigger node this is just fantastic.
So, this is a great examples of
how visual studios doing more that and you know, it's just it's
just great to see all right so now.
This...going to do the summary go ahead and.
Thanks users.
Thank you
...in visual studio that's available we've talked about up can usage yeah.
...very hitting...you figure
that's a good and we have shown you what open-source
we're supporting better on windows and what's available in the sdk so now what are the decor is what's
in it for us developer first.
You can chipper apps faster you can get to the market, market
faster you have for some of the cutting-edge open-source we have windows api for all
...so you don't need to go worry about on boarding and open-source project
into your enterprise up for say like go around
...all that so we've taken some of that overhead away by providing windows aps or some of these.
...into the...so again easier to take a dependency on they're
easier to maintain now because now for a lot of these you can be getting updates from windows you
need to separately google and update the...that...your app ...easier
to troubleshooting so you already have this open-source community and forums but now you
can also get support from the windows development center and we would have samples therefore you guys.
And, it's easier to...platform apps the with
...say you're coming to a you want to make
universal windows application you coming from a different platform you don't need to re architect
your entire app because a certain database library isn't available doesn't work as well.
You can also to deliver better user experiences so in the all
join example that we saw you saw...notification come...when your tools for done.
So, because it's all supported by the platform not only that more performing
but it comes with like less permission...user experience this...you
...to check a button being like yell at this bug doctor meets all hundred by...code.
And, then because it's supported insidethe operating system
...done special work you keep the memory footprint...and to make it faster.
So, this is a big but this was like a big overview of all the different projects
we've been working on...deep dives happening throughout build and goes you to check
them out there's a deeper dive into entity framework the all join session already happen you can
get it online there's one angle the...gs one I'm really excited about
what do check that out as well so here's a list of ...
And, then please do follow-up with us we will be hanging around in the quick star...just
...there's a question answer around right after this we really
want your feedback up if you have ideas and how we can do this better
I'll come talk to us if you have complains get them off your...we're here for you guys
would that thank you very much and thanks for coming enjoy the rest of
...of build and I hope we could show you the stuff working but anyways
...that's probably thank you?